hello and welcome to the policy Bazar
show here on Republic TV most financial
experts will tell you that the most
important thing about financial planning
is getting yourself a good health
insurance we are going to talk about
that and more one of the things that a
lot of us believe is that if we are
working our employer offers us a group
cover medical cover a health cover and
that's more than enough for us now is
that really enough those are some of the
questions we are going to seek to answer
with our esteemed panelists joining me
today is Annika Agarwal who's the chief
marketing officer at max Bupa one of the
leading health insurance companies in
the country and also with me is Amit
Chopra who's the business head for
health insurance at policy bazaar which
has been a disruptor as far as enabling
millions of Indians to buy their
insurance online thank you very much
both of you for coming by before we you
know get into the aspect of a group
cover versus individual I just want to
get a quick insight from both of you on
are you seeing a change in the youth
especially becoming a little more aware
about buying health insurance at an
early age so if you look at the young
Millennials of today I think there are
little more conscious about you know
their financial spending what they want
to do with their life and their goals
from that perspective yes they're a
little more aware in terms of financial
protection and we see a lot of
youngsters today buying health insurance
at an earlier age if you look at the
average age when a customer bought a
health insurance it was usually at the
time of either their marriage all you
know when their first child is born
today we see more and more young ones
buying health insurance and an ideal age
to buy a health insurance cover today is
actually between 28 years to almost 30
to 33 years so people in their first
jobs are in their second jobs just
before they start their journey of you
know marriage children actually are
buying covers for themselves
and not just for their parents so let's
talk a little about you know the health
cover the group covers that employers
provide to their employees now those who
are an employee already probably are
aware of this maybe you are already
covered by your company but for those
who are not aware and many may be not
aware what exactly is the group cover
that an employer provides to its
employees
so as government guidelines every
employer has to provide some sort of
health insurance cover now typically at
the at the labor levels it's the ESIC
provided cover that's that's given at a
beyond a certain level it's typically a
group health cover that the employer
will purchase from an insurance company
and give it to all their employees the
catch there is everybody does not really
understand the exact features and the
coverage is that the group health cover
provides so just to give you a simple
perspective roughly about sixty percent
of all health insurance that's provided
by an employer has a sum insured of this
two lakh rupees there are a lot of
limitations there are a lot of sub
limits on room rent on the kind of
diseases which will be covered or there
are sub limits so for example for a
cataract thing only about 21 thousand
rupees will be paid so there are a lot
of these limitations which customers
today aren't really aware so they may
think that their employer provided
health insurance enough but that may not
be true so that is something that that
urge everybody to actually understand
from the current policy there is a
perception Annika that you know when you
take a group cover it covers a lot more
diseases than an individual cover does
is that true or is that a myth so you
know there are certain advantages that
come as when you are a part of a group
policy the first and primary advantage
is that there are no pre-existing
disease waiting periods so if I enroll
into a policy today and I am a diabetic
let's say I will be covered from day one
so that's a natural advantage that a
group cover offers you and that's true
but what happens is that you know if you
have an individual cover and you've
served your waiting periods early enough
then you get a more comprehensive
coverage with your individual cover we
also need to understand that you know
health insurance with rising medical
inflation and healthcare costs is
becoming expensive
so employers are actually reducing your
summon shortened coverages azimuth
mentioned they may be certain sub limits
in your group policy which may not be
there in your individual policy so sub
limits for diseases like cataract knee
replacement will not be there in your
individual policy if you look at your
policy carefully so you get a more
comprehensive coverage and none of these
features that you mentioned come with a
group cover so some of them do but it is
dependent on your employer there is very
little flexibility that you have as an
employee and I think another important
point is actually the coverage of your
dependents today most insurance policies
which are group policies would cover an
individual and immediate family which is
you know your spouse and your children
but parent coverage today in group
policies is shrinking so if you need to
buy a cover which covers the entire
family which is you yourself your
children your spouse and your parents
you should look at at a family floater
plan what are some of the restrictions
that a group cover comes with there are
three major limitations you have to say
so number one the sum insured some
insured is typically 2 lakhs 3 lakhs
doesn't really go beyond it which may be
less in the current scheme of things
where the medical inflation has is
really really high so even for a for a
very very normal typical kind of a
medical complication that summons what
we get exhausted very very quickly so
that's one second is sub limits within
the policy so for example a typical
cataract surgery for both eyes would end
up costing about 2 lakh rupees
the typical limit in a group policy is
about 2 anywhere thousand rupees as an
example so the customer will eventually
have to shell out that kind of money
from from their own pocket the other
restriction is what happens when you
leave the job now there are two
scenarios that can happen you leave the
job you go into someone others another
job and you get another policy there
that's a possibility yes what you don't
realize is there is a big gamble over
there what if the new company does not
have a policy as good as your current
company what if it does not cover your
dependents is only covering the employer
employee what happens in case you know
it has a very different policy
altogether so that that's something that
a customer does not think of right now
and
specifically for the youth which may
currently think that you know I am fit
in fine right now I don't really need
health insurance but they don't realize
is let's say 20 30 years down the line
when they actually retire and they would
be leaving their employer they may have
some pre-existing disease like let's say
diabetes or hypertension that may not
get covered at all so at that stage you
may not even be able to buy a retail
health insurance policy or it will be a
policy which will be very expensive and
at the same time with a lot of
limitations so that is something which
you won't see right now but it will come
to bite you at a later stage that is
that is something which is very very
critical for the youth of today to
realize now rather than you know realize
it 20 years down the line many employers
annika give the employee an option to
say that how much cover do you want you
know you made the point that parents for
example being included in the cover is a
is a principal shrinking but many of
them you know give you various slabs and
they say that you know do you want to
pay a little extra and get your parents
covered you want to pay a little extra
get your children covered are you saying
that all of this may not be enough for
an individual so I think there are two
things one is of course it may not be
enough from you know the coverage point
of view from a some in short perspective
as Amit said it's only 2 to 3 lakh
rupees even if it is 5 lakhs 5 years
down the line it may not be enough for
you and I think the other important
point is insurance is always about
protection for you know the uncertain
and for future somewhere we do not
realize when we are planning when we are
setting our financial goals that 10
years from now if this is not enough for
me or if my parents are not covered
adequately then you know this is a large
dent in the pocket and at that point in
time you may not get the right insurance
cover that is the most important aspect
that you should buy it when you're
healthy so that you can get the right
sum insured because otherwise it will
come with limitations it will come with
exclusions in your policy which you may
not point because sometimes we do not
read the fine print of our insurance
policy you know as consumers it's very
important to understand that there will
be certain limitations and exclusions if
you have a pre-existing disease or if
you are of a certain age whereas if
you're paying your premiums early and
you have a policy which is continuing
for
10 to 12 years then you've covered all
of those off you don't have any
exclusions in your policy and as your
age increases and the chances and
probability of you you know having a
critical illness or a pre all you know
lifestyle disease like diabetes and
hypertension come in you are protected
so it's about adequacy of coverage it's
about covering your entire family and
it's also about saying you know what are
the right things for me in an insurance
policy which is flexibility and
customization which sometimes you may
not get in a group cover ok we take a
short break here on the policy Bazaar
show when we come back we continue to
discuss the merit of having an
individual cover in addition to a group
cover that your company where you're
employed may be offering you an ACOG our
Val and Amit Chopra will be there as
well we'll be back in a short while
welcome back to the policy bizarre show
we are talking about health insurance
and more specifically about whether it's
enough to have an employer provided
health cover for yourself or do you also
need an individual cover the unanimous
verdict so far from the panelists has
been it is not enough to depend solely
on what your employer is providing you
it's also important to have your own
cover and own individual cover I'm it
just to close the piece on the employer
versus individual cover I think one of
the things that makes people go for an
employer cover or at least used to make
them go for an employer cover was the
ease but has the ease factor become much
more simpler today the big misconception
that we've always seen a lot of
customers having that getting as the
insurance plan needs you to get a
medical check-up done and typical
typical mentality a lot of us have is to
be we are afraid of medicals because we
never know what might come out of the
medical policy eventually right so if I
am somebody who smokes and who drinks I
am very very afraid about going to a
medical check-up because you know right
now I'm confident that I am fit in fine
but you never know what might come out
of that checkup so we really shy when it
comes to going for a medical
what we don't know is that if you are up
to the age of sixty years there's
actually no need to even go get a
medical check-up at all you you get an
instant policy it covers you it provides
all the coverages from day one itself
even if you have a disease like let's
say diabetes or hypertension you still
actually don't need to go through a
medical check-up most of the insurance
policies today get issued through a
process called tele underwriting where a
qualified doctor from the insurance
company will ask a set of questions and
based on those questions the policy will
be issued instantly so it's actually
pretty simple yes definitely the process
of you know filling up the form the
payments there's no paperwork me right
now like it used to always be the
process of paying is much simpler you
can buy a policy up to three years
upfront and that gives you a discount as
well
so from an ease perspective yes
definitely think they've improved but
the big myths that a lot of people have
that you know I am afraid of going for a
medical check-up and that's why I would
never buy health insurance policy that's
actually not true often it happens that
I might be just starting out in my
career I may be twenty-five twenty-six
first job I'm listening to the two of
you and saying okay let me get myself a
health cover but at this point I may be
only able to get myself say a five lakh
cover maybe that's the only amount I can
afford in terms of premium is there
flexibility that I can with every
passing year or keep increasing my cover
so you can increase your some insured
you can move to a better product a
better brand so all of those options are
available every year when you renew okay
so if you want to increase you know from
five lakhs to one curve you can do that
next year okay so all of those options
are available but with the same
insurance company or I can port it out
to another insurance company you can do
both you can do both see also what you
have to realize is over time products
are evolving significantly so again cut
back to ten years ten years back the
products were much simpler there were a
lot of restrictions that they offered on
room rent for example earlier products
typically had a 1% room rent limit which
means if you have a 5 lakh rupees I'm
insured the room the maximum room rent
that you could afford is five thousand
rupees in a hospital which maybe was
fine ten years back but right now it's
not so today
good health insurance plans don't have a
ruminant capping so you can get a single
private room up to any standard so you
go to the most expensive Hospital you
can always get this in single private
room there it's covered in your health
insurance policy
additionally there are there are some
products which are even able to offer
you a suite room in a hospital for
example it's almost the most luxurious
room in a hospital you can go and you
can get treated over there so just to
take that point further Annika how would
you describe what is a good plan plan
you know plans are evolving and azimuth
said you could move to a different plan
but also your own insurance plan your
insurance company would enhance every
two to three years and you automatically
get upgraded to a new plan which is as
per the current needs right so you know
you may have room rent enhancements as
Ameth mentioned in your current plan
also you know every two to three years
you should look at your own some insured
and see that's adequate for you most
insurers would give you that option to
actually upgrade your some insured as
and when you feel the need so if you
look at a good insurance plan I think
you should look at comprehensive
coverage for hospitalization which would
include not just basic hospitalization
but coverage for day care procedures
alternative treatments today most plans
cover for pre and post expenses of
hospitalization you should get that
coverage in beyond a basic
hospitalization cover you can buy a
top-up for a critical illness like
cancer which is increasing so you could
actually do you know a lump sum payout
when a critical illness occurs so you
could have a base hospitalization plan
then top it up with a critical illness
plan there are also plans today that
offer wellness features and to your
point you know around increase of some
insured so you could do that yourself
but a lot of plans in the market today
would actually offer you automatic some
ensured increases so there is a concept
of sum insured refill so as and when you
know you extend your policy duration so
let's say in a period of five years your
sum insured can actually double so it
almost gives you inflation protection so
you know max pupas go active plan has a
feature called I protect which actually
gives you inflation protection
automatically ten percent year-on-year
as you know the plan moves forward so
you don't have to worry and think
about you know what's my rights I'm
insured when do I increase it many plans
have that option so you know there are
these refill benefits available as well
and many plans have a no claim option as
well so you know if you've not claimed
and you've got claim three years let's
say three or four years you're some
insured but increase with every claim
Fleer so it's almost like a loyalty
reward for the customer and it also
helps them you know keep up with medical
inflation so Amit since there are you
know so many insurance companies out
there and probably each insurance
company has a bouquet of products as
Anika mentioned how do I go about
sifting through when you know a company
like yours actually helps me make that
decision so how easy is it I mean there
are so many features Aaronic I just
talked about that one was not even aware
of how easy is it or how do I go about
as a consumer if I'm listening to you I
want to go and buy a policy and I
probably have certain very specific
needs of my own depending on my
background my history my family history
how do I go about purchasing it so there
are three broad decisions that you have
to make when you're looking to buy a
health insurance plan you have to think
of what Simon showed you only by what
kind of features you want to buy because
that will decide the kind of product you
would end up buying and third is which
brand do you want to go with see health
insurance is a it is a complex purchase
yes because this is something that
you're buying forever now this is
something that you'll retain for your
entire lifetime so you would want to
always make the right decision what is
very important here to also understand
is do not to be biased or get influenced
by somebody who may be selling you a
specific plan because of some commercial
reasons that the the person may have
used to see that a lot in the past ages
you know when in past past years rather
when you know an agent would come and
want to sell a policy because because of
the kind of commercial arrangements that
he has but yeah coming back so there are
three broad areas that one should look
at the first one is some insured now
what someone showed to buy is pretty
much a factor of two two decision points
one is what's your lifestyle stage or
what's what's your family like are you
looking to buy an individual cover or
are you looking to buy a cover for you
know
wife for your family for your kids for
your parents so it completely depends on
that and it depends on the kind of
budget you have you know in an ideal
case if there is no budget constraint I
would I would prefer buying the highest
sum in short possible because that
ensures that I am covered against
anything possible that happens to me but
if there are budget limitations yes you
should look at as Anika was saying
earlier probably or 15 to 20 lakh cover
because that will give you adequate
coverage against critical illnesses as
well as any day-to-day unless that
happens specifically you know
specifically for a family okay so that's
one the second thing you look at is what
kind of features you want to have in
your insurance policy and today we're
seeing a lot of innovation happening
over there so do you want
OPD being covered in your health
insurance policy or not do you want
maternity being covered or not so if
you're planning a kid let's say two
three years four years down the line
then you might want to get a plan which
covers our maternity expenses as well do
you want to get global coverage so in
case something something critical
happens you can actually go outside
India and get treated at the best
hospitals in the world do you want a no
claim bonus and to what extent do you
want to go in the no claim bonus or the
refill as any comment and what that does
is it gives you adequate coverage in
case something's already happened in the
ER and you have exhausted your entire
some insurance so based on these
parameters you decide the kind of
product you want to go with the other
thing is if you have any existing any
existing disease so for example if you
if a customer today has diabetes there
are plans which are specific to diabetes
which offers diabetes specific need
features to the customer and then
they're generic plans which will put a
four year waiting period so just to give
you an example today a plan can give you
day one coverage on diabetes as well if
you are an existing diabetes patient
whereas you also have plans which put a
four year waiting period you also have
plans which put a permanent exclusion on
diabetes so depending upon the kind of
asleep rising varies accordingly so
depending upon your budget and your
feature requirement you decide and the
third thing is the brand you want to go
with so and that depends on a number of
factors again it depends on what kind of
cashless network the specific brand has
because in Metro cities it does not
really matter that much because all of
the large health insurance companies
have presents across you know all of
large hospitals but let's say if you are
somebody who travels a lot who goes out
into rural areas a lot you would want to
look at the coverage the cashless
network coverage in those specific
cities so that is very critical when you
make when you make a decision and she
eventually health insurance is all about
trust it it you know how much do you
trust health insurance company because
you would call them up when you are in a
state of distress you are probably in a
hospital with you being admitted or
somebody very very nearby to you
admitted so it's very important if it's
if you trust a specific brand if you
trust you know that they will be with
you at the time of claim that makes a
very critical decision when it comes to
the brand so to summarize it's a
function of some insured what kind of
features you want to buy and the kind of
brand you want to buy typically all
large brands would have some kind of
offering for you with within all of
these three factors so based on that is
where a customer should make a decision
which is where actually comparison
becomes very very critical today there
are about 25 as companies which offer
health insurance plans it's very
important that you actually compare and
come to a conclusion to what plan you're
buying you should look at all the
features read the fine print as Annika
was saying because it's important
because you would not realize it right
now maybe five years down the line when
you are at the state of a claim is when
you realize that
oops my policy does not cover this or
there is a copay attached to this so
very important to compare read the
policy document carefully understand
exactly what you are buying before you
buy moving on to our next segment which
is the mythbuster
the myth is anneka that I am young
nothing's going to happen to me I'm very
healthy at this point of time why do I
need an individual insurance my group
cover is enough so I think we should
bust that myth fact number one there is
a growing incidence of lifestyle
diseases even at a very young age fact
number two if you buy it later when
you've already got a disease you may not
get adequate coverage and three you know
if you have a corporate cover you may
not have enough some in short or
coverage so yes you do need a
hospitalization cover and you do need it
early specifically I think in your
twenties so if I'm young I really you
know there are two reasons why I will
think like this one is I'll always think
that nothing like this will ever happen
to me it's very easy to bust that myth
actually look at how many celebrities
around us who were all fit and fine who
suddenly got cancer secondly I would
feel like that if I because I think that
you know in case something happens to me
I will take care of that from my own
savings what we don't realize is you
know there have been so many instances
where all because of critical unless all
my savings or vanished completely
vanished of all what I had garnered in
my lifetime because I do pay like 20 30
40 lakh rupees at the time of my illness
so these are the two reasons why I think
people don't realize it right now but
yes it is something that somewhere at
the back of the mind a lot of us know we
just - too scared to accept it so go out
there get yourself health insurance
cover as soon as you can because it only
gets more expensive and complex as you
go up in age so get yourself a cover
immediately it will come cheaper it will
come without any hassles as you heard
the panelists talk about and then you
can keep adding on to it and as it
evolves as your own life evolves okay
that's all the time we have in this
edition of the policy bizarre show will
be back with lots more thanks for
watching
[Music]